We discuss other forms of heart disease
adnauseium like atherosclerosis, the
plaque buildup in our arteries. But the
reality is that there are other forms of
heart disease that plague us as well.
What is most fascinating is that we can
detect these forms of heart disease
because of a hormone that gets secreted
from our heart like a check engine light
before you realize you haven't changed
the oil in your old car in a while. The
beautiful thing is that we can
communicate back to our heart repairing
the issue before it causes a type of
heart disease called heart failure. So
let me take you along for a scientific
ride to understand this heart secreted
hormone, how you can easily order a test
for it, heart failure, and how to reduce
your risk assuming that there is any to
begin with. When you think of hormones,
you probably think of the ones that are
released out of your pancreas like
insulin or by your adrenal glands like
cortisol. But many tissues of your body
secrete hormones. Your heart being one
of many. The hormone I'm talking about
is BNP or brain natrioretic peptide or
more recently renamed to Btype
natrioretic peptide. The name doesn't
really matter too much. Just know that
BMP is secreted by your heart muscle
cells. Now, the reason it's released by
your heart cells is what we're
interested in. When stress is applied to
the heart cells, like excessive amounts
of blood volume pushing against the
heart wall, the heart muscle cells
called myioardioittes release BNP.
Ultimately, what you need to know for us
to progress in this story and understand
the importance of BMP to you is that BMP
is secreted more as your heart
experiences more stress from blood
pushing against the structure of the
heart in an attempt to reduce this
stress. Obviously, saying things like
more stress doesn't really sound good,
but that doesn't necessarily mean
there's a relationship with increased
heart failure either. So when we split
people without heart failure into three
groups, a low BMP group, a moderate BMP,
and a high BMP group, we see a striking
result. All I'll say is the higher the
lines, the more heart failure occurred
in these people. Clearly a step-wise
fashion, as BMP levels rise, heart
failure risk is raised. Now, this is
associative evidence, meaning that BMP
is not necessarily causing heart
failure. In fact, we aren't even
interested in determining if BMP's
positive relationship to heart failure.
We just want to know if it is related,
as in if there are elevated levels, does
that track with heart failure. And the
answer is yes, confirmed in scientific
reviews like this one as well. The great
part about BMP testing is that it's
readily available at most labs in one of
two forms. So, BMP directly or NT
ProBNP. Now, when it comes to testing,
there's one thing to know. The values
offered in testing can be a bit
deceptive. For example, if a person was
tested for acute or emergency heart
failure diagnosis, they'd be looking for
values in the hundreds of poggrams per
milliliter. At that point, you're
probably hospitalized. So, it doesn't
really apply here. And the study that we
just covered was looking at people
without heart failure who were split
into three groups with much lower blood
values. For women, the high condition
was anything above 15.8 and for men,
anything above 12.8. I'll also mention
that BMP can be artificially high after
strenuous exercise and other stressors
of the sort. So testing should be done
just like most other scenarios in a
baseline estate as possible. There's
more to say on testing in a bit, but I'd
like to get into some solutions. What
can be done to reduce risk of heart
failure? Now, before we touch on that,
if you're curious on BMP and how it
relates to other diseases like stroke,
coronary heart disease, mortality as a
whole, how BMP affects your kidneys,
your adrenal glands, and your arteries,
and another protein released by your
heart, and the relationship to heart
health, then check out my extended video
along with an accompanying article
standard with all my analyses. It's
included as a Physionic Insider, my
premium research platform. You also get
a private podcast in case you want
everything delivered in a monthly audio
episode only and I do regular live
sessions with the insider community.
Anyway, there's a lot of benefits of
being an insider. Check out the
membership using the link in the
description. I hope to see you there. In
this study, participants without heart
failure but with elevated potential for
developing heart failure were placed on
a standard treatment program or a
treatment program that was identical but
included routine measurements of blood
BMP. So the only difference between the
two groups here was the personal
physician's knowledge of their patients
BMP or not. The control group, the
physicians had no idea, but they knew
all the other heart disease risk factors
and the intervention there. The
physicians also were clued in on their
patients BMP and were allowed to act
accordingly. Now, if the lines go up,
that means that there's more
cardiovascular disease, not necessarily
heart failure, but I can tell you that
there were similar results for heart
failure as well. Clearly, when all
participants are included, there's a
reduced risk of cardiovascular events
when BMP is known. And this is
especially true when limiting the data
to just those with especially high
subclinical BMP levels of over 50. This
tells us two things. One, being aware of
your BMP can lead to better health care
and be protective against heart failure.
And two, having a capable physician that
can make adjustments based on your BMP
values inclusive of other risk factors
can make a tremendous difference to your
risk. At this point, you may be thinking
to yourself that you should get your BMP
checked, and there's nothing inherently
wrong with that, except it's likely
unnecessary for some. So, hold that
thought until we return to it. Now, this
only tells us that being educated about
BMP, tracking it yearly and addressing
it as a first step. The next step is
how? Well, since physicians in the
intervention arm of the study could do
whatever they wanted to mitigate risk,
we can't pinpoint any single action that
caused this benefit. But that won't stop
us. Because if we hearken back to my
introduction to this topic where I said
this
now, the reason it's released by your
heart cells is what we're interested in.
When stress is applied to the heart
cells, like excessive amounts of blood
volume pushing against the heart wall,
the heart muscle cells called
myioardioittes release BNP. You have to
think to yourself why blood volume would
be pushing against the heart wall to
such a degree that it would cause the
heart cells to release BMP to reduce
heart stress. The answer is high blood
pressure. In fact, when we look at
long-term studies, there is a
consistently high risk of heart failure
with high blood pressure, which is even
stronger with clinically high BNP
levels. The only issue is that these
studies are associative, making it more
difficult to directly point the finger
at blood pressure and improve BMP and
even more importantly heart failure.
Naturally, we turn to randomized control
trials for these kinds of situations.
And wouldn't you know it, there's many.
And they all generally point the same
direction. like here. This is a direct
measure of heart failure between blood
pressure lowering treatment in red and
not treating high blood pressure in
blue. The higher the lines, the more
heart failure. So obviously reducing
blood pressure reduces heart failure
risk. However, I can also tell you that
reducing blood pressure also reduces BMP
release. A coincidence? Not likely.
Knowing the intertwined nature of it
all. Let me discuss this last point and
the testing again because I should offer
some context. While it is expected for
BMP to drop when normalizing blood
pressure to below 120 over 80, it does
not always normalize for a number of
reasons that we don't really need to get
into. So, here's how I'd think about it.
It's a good tool to assess risk before
heart failure, but it is less
informative if you are looking for a
gauge on your continued heart failure
risk after risk has already presented.
In addition to that, if you're healthy,
normal weight, not dealing with any
chronic health issues, it's probably
unnecessary except maybe if you're an
ultra long distance athlete, to consider
this test. The people that will get the
most use out of it are people with type
two diabetes, people who have been
overweight for many years, those with
obviously long-term high blood pressure
and the like. The risk is exceedingly
low if you don't have a family history
or your other health metrics look normal
and probably not a priority to track
unless you're really into knowing every
aspect of your health. Honestly, when it
comes to heart health, there's plenty of
other things to do like what I cover in
this next video right here. Thanks for
tuning in. I hope this fascinated you as
much as it did me. I guess I'll see you
in the next video. Okay, go ahead. I'll
uh I'll meet I'll meet you over there.
No, no, no. I promise.
Fine. I'll I'll go first.